Guide to the Paul Kagan Utopian Communities Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
The third subseries, Personal Papers, is organized into Correspondence, Documents, Writings by Walter Millsap, Writings by Others, Photographs and Postcards, and Printed Material. Walter Millsap's correspondence with his parents includes several postcards from Llano del Rio in 1917, and from Newllano in 1919 (box 7, folders 160-161). There are also personal letters to and from other family members, including Walter's grandfather A. J. Millsap, Walter's father Leander W. Millsap, and Walter's mother, Cara Millsap. (The Record of Family Traits in the Documents section contains biographical information about his family, and biographical essays can be found in Writings by Walter Millsap.) Finally, there is a large quantity of correspondence with Eric Gast, an ex-Llanoite, regarding property that Millsap bought from Gast in return for some Llano stock. A related folder of documents is filed in the Documents section (box 8, folder 179).
Photographs and Postcards contains approximately 140 photographs, including cabinet photographs, one tintype and a large number of small format snapshots, consisting of formal photographs and snapshots of family, friends and city scenes. Photographers represented in the files are H. Cook of Woodland, California; Harold McCurry, Sacramento; Hemenway, Vacaville, Cal.; J.C. Shinkle, Woodland, Cal.; J.E.D. Baldwin, Rembrandt Studio, Sacramento; Soracco, California Art Studio. There are also photographs signed L.W.M., presumably Walter Millsap himself. Printed Material contains a large number of serials and pamphlets that reflect Millsap's interest in socialist activities, and includes copies of Upton Sinclair's I, Governor of California and The Lie Factory Starts (box 13, folder 242).
Series II, William and Lucille Riker Papers (1876-1969), (boxes 14-17) is organized into two subseries: Holy City and Personal Papers. As with the Millsap Papers, the Riker Papers include source material gathered from other colonists by William Riker. References to Irvin B. Fisher, chief engineer at Holy City, and later president of the Perfect Christian Divine Way, are frequent in the Holy City Correspondence and Photographs. The Papers relating to Holy City are arranged into Correspondence, Documents, Writings, Photographs and Postcards, Other Visual Material, and Printed Material. The bulk of the materials range in dates from 1940-1965; however, a large amount of undated material is also present. The Documents contain a file of financial records from the 1960s kept by Joseph Albert, Manager of Holy City. The Writings consist of manuscripts and paste-ups for Holy City newsletters (probably produced by William Riker); these have been left as found, as their lack of a discernable order is aggravated by their poor condition. Photographs and Postcards contains images of the Perfect Christian Divine Way School of Mastery in San Francisco, and include ten cyanotypes. Other Visual Material contains banners, illustrations for talks and displays, and posters and signs advertising the Perfect Christian Divine Way doctrine.
The subseries Personal Papers is arranged into William Riker, Lucille Riker, and Others and contains correspondence, documents, photographs, and printed material. Some of William Riker's earliest letters are exchanges with Irvin Fisher, who was incarcerated in the California State Prison at San Quentin. William Riker's correspondence also features letters of protest from Riker to the U.S. Attorney and the F.B.I. regarding "libelous and defamatory" statements made about him in The New Day by Father Divine, and includes a letter from J. Edgar Hoover dated April 9, 1943 (box 16, folder 281). The correspondence and documents reflect William Riker's attempt to get his former lawyer, Melvin Belli, disbarred. Lucille Riker's papers concern her attempts to get her song lyrics set to music and published. A copy of the sheet music for her song, "Please Don't Leave Me Daddy," is present, as are other song lyrics and a short story. Also in this section are formal portrait photographs of the Rikers taken by Leon's Photo Studio (San Francisco), Hartsook (San Francisco) and other California photographers.
Series III, John and Agnes Varian Papers (1893-1935), (box 18) contains source material on Halcyon: Correspondence, Writings, Printed Material, and Other Papers. Their correspondence consists principally of incoming letters. The first folder contains letters received at the beginning of the Varians' studies in the Eastern School of Theosophy, while they lived in Ireland, and also after their move to California. In them, the Varians discuss Theosophical ideas, and events in the Society in the United States and Ireland, with various associates/fellow Theosophists, including Annie Besant, William Q. Judge, and George William Russell. Correspondence written after their move to California in 1905 reflects the Varians' involvement in events at Halcyon and contains letters from Temple members about events at Halcyon, though the Varians themselves lived at Palo Alto until after 1912. A topic of particular interest seems to have been the controversy over the marriage of Dr. William Dower to Mrs. Jane Kent. Letters from both Dr. Dower and Mrs. Kent, as well as Francia LaDue, are present. The remaining papers include notes on Temple teachings, printed Temple pamphlets, and photographs of the Temple of the People and individuals there.
Series IV, Paul Kagan Research Files (1845-1980), (boxes 19-34) is organized into seventeen subseries. Ten contain source materials on utopian communities discussed in Paul Kagan's book, New World Utopias: Fountaingrove, Halcyon, Holy City, Icaria Speranza, Kaweah, Krotona and Ojai Valley, Llano del Rio and Newllano, Pisgah Grande, Point Loma, and the Tassajara Zen Mountain Center. The other seven subseries represent modern utopian or shared communities that Kagan planned to include in his book, in a closing chapter that was later abandoned. Generally, documentation on the communities featured in his book is more extensive than that for those not treated.
Unlike Series I-III, each of which is defined largely by provenance, Series IV contains material without unity of provenance: there is both original material collected by Paul Kagan, as well as secondary material created during his research for the book, including additional material about Llano del Rio and Newllano, Holy City, and Halcyon, beyond that acquired from Millsap (Series I), Riker (Series II), or Varian (Series III) respectively.
A particular strength of Series IV is its photographic component: Fountaingrove, Krotona and Ojai Valley, Llano del Rio and Newllano, and Point Loma are especially well represented. There are vintage photographic prints, Paul Kagan's own photographs (used as illustrations for his book), as well as copy prints and negatives acquired from a variety of sources. Where possible, the institution holding the original images has been identified and contacted, and permission has been obtained to retain the copy prints and negatives in this collection, with the understanding that they are for reference use only, and are not to be reproduced. Other copy prints and negatives include ones whose source has not been identified as well as those that were made, probably by Kagan, from the original photographs in the first three series. No attempt has been made to match Paul Kagan's negatives to originals or to copy prints in the collection.
Almost every community file contains Paul Kagan's notes, as well as photocopies of the historian Robert Hine's notes. (Robert Hine is the author of California's Utopian Colonies, published in 1966.) Hine's notes are present only for reference use; they may not be reproduced. The community files also include pamphlets, clippings, and other printed material, as well as oral histories for individuals at Krotona and Ojai Valley, Llano del Rio and Newllano, Pisgah Grande, and Point Loma. (The oral history on Llano and Newllano is a transcript of an interview with Walter Millsap.)
The Farm is represented primarily by printed material, as are the Lama Foundation and the Self-Realization Fellowship. Fountaingrove is represented chiefly by photographs, which include many portraits of Japanese-Americans taken by Japanese-American photographers, a number of views of the Fountaingrove winery and countryside, and one image of a San Francisco street taken after the earthquake in 1906. Photographers represented in these files are: Imai (San Francisco), J. Ross (Santa Rosa, Cal.), Uchiyama (San Francisco), Piggott (Santa Rosa, Cal.), F. O. Haussler (Oakland), Taber (San Francisco), Tsuji Photo Studio (Oakland), J. H. Peters (San Francisco), H. Kempvanee (Santa Rosa, Cal.), T. J. Bruce (Marshall, Texas), Z. Yamabe (San Francisco).
For Halcyon, there is an essay by Harold Forgostein, guardian in chief of the Temple of the People (box 23, folder 384). Krotona and Ojai Valley are represented primarily by photographs and writings. The photographs include both formal portraits and snapshots, three complete albums featuring views of Krotona, and two folders of disbound leaves from albums. Photographers represented here include Chas. W. Beam, Hollywood Blvd, Los Angeles; R. H. Stone, Los Angeles; Bryan-Brandenburg Co. Engravers, Electrotypers, Los Angeles; Witzel, Los Angeles; W. Schrempf, Hollywood. The seven folders of writings, some of which are undated, contain typescripts of essays by Annie Besant, and printed books by Annie Besant, H. P. Blavatsky, W. Q. Judge, and J. Krishnamurti. There is also an unsigned oil portrait of Annie Besant, measuring 26 1/2" x 22 (box 30, folder 475).
The section on Llano del Rio and Newllano contains photographs by Paul Kagan and Ernest S. Wooster, which appear to have come from a source other than Walter Millsap, whose photographs are to be found in Series I. There are also numerous copy prints and copy negatives: presumably, these were made from Walter Millsap photographs and printed material in the first series.
The files for Pisgah Grande, besides containing three oral histories, include "blest cloths" (squares of cloth about 2" x 3" with several Bible chapters and verses listed on them: box 31, folder 514) from Pisgah Grande and from Pisgah in Tennessee. Point Loma's section includes portraits of Point Loma colonists and photographs of productions of Greek plays. Two folders of photographs are from published photographic series produced there: the Loma Homestead Photographic Series and the Lomaland Photographic Series. In addition, there are four folders of photocopies or carbons of correspondence, documents, and writings belonging to Iverson L. Harris, a Point Loma alumnus who ran in the 1970s a Theosophical nonprofit educational and religious corporation named Point Loma Publications, Inc. (Correspondence between Paul Kagan and Harris is located in the New World Utopias Correspondence section of Series V.)
Other Communes contains mailings, pamphlets, newspapers, broadsides, and photocopies about additional utopian communities and related organizations, arranged in a general alphabetical run, by commune, except for the more extensive groups of material on the Farallones Institute Integral Urban House, Lemurian Fellowship, and Resource One, which are filed separately. This section also contains a number of periodicals, and a large Bible whose provenance is unknown.
Series V, Paul Kagan's Writings (1970-1976), (boxes 35-37) is organized into two subseries: New World Utopias and Other Writings. The New World Utopias subseries contains material about the publication of Kagan's book. The Correspondence is arranged alphabetically and includes both carbons of letters Kagan sent out and originals that he received. There are letters about the progress of his research, letters from publishers declining to accept his book for publication, an extensive correspondence file with Penguin Books, and letters of permission from institutions and individuals for photographs published in the book. The subseries also contains chapter drafts, layout proofs, and setting typescripts, a copy of the book itself (box 36, folder 664), and reviews of the book, as well as photographs of an exhibition based on the book, held at the Oakland Museum in 1975, and posters advertising the exhibition. The second subseries, Other Writings, contains material (including correspondence) pertaining to several articles Paul Kagan wrote, all dealing with the utopian movement.
Oversize contains oversize material from series I-V, and is listed in box order.
Appendix A: Materials Transferred to the Printed Book Collection
Holy City: The Enlightener Edited by the P.C.D.W., San Francisco, Cal.
.....1916 May 15-Aug 15
.....1916 Oct 15-Nov 15
.....1916 Dec 15-1917 Apr 15 (Vol 1, Nos. 8-12)
.....1917 May 15-1917 Jul 15 (Vol 2, Nos. 1-2)
.....1917 Aug 15-1918 Apr 15 (Vol 2, Nos. 4-12)
.....1918 May 15-1919 Feb 15 (Vol 3, Nos. 1-10)
.....1919 Apr 15: (Vol 3, No. 12)
.....1919 May 15-1920 Mar 15 (Vol 4, Nos. 1-11)
.....1920 May 15-1920 Dec 15 (Vol 5, Nos. 1-9) Pamphlets and broadsides published by the PCDW headquarters about PCDW doctrine and Holy City. Llano del Rio and Newllano: The Clifton Tray of Food 4 Thot .....1937 Feb 18-25 (Nos. 258-259)
.....Continued as Clifton's Food for Thot Los Angeles
.....1949 Oct 7 (No. 919)
.....1950 Mar 2 (No. 940)
.....1950 Nov 16 (No. 977)
.....1951 Aug 16 (No. 1016)
.....1951 Sep 6 (No. 1019)
.....1951 Oct 4 (No. 1023)
.....1951 Dec 6 (No. 1032)
.....1952 Apr 3 (No. 1049) The Colonist .....1960 Sep Colony Co-operator Published by the Llano Co-operative Colony at Leesville, Louisiana
.....1918 Sep-1919 Feb (Vol. 1, Nos. 4-8)
.....1919 Apr-1919 Jul/Aug (Vol. 1, Nos. 10-12)
.....1919 Sep (Vol. 2, No. 1)
.....1920 Jan/Feb (Vol. 2, No. 3) The Llano Colonist Newllano, Louisiana
.....1931 Aug 29-Sep 19 (Vol. 11, Nos. 1118-1121)
.....1935 Jun 22 (Vol. 15, No. 1509)
.....1935 Jul 27 (Vol. 15, No. 1514)
.....1936 Mar 14 (Vol. 15, No. 1547)
.....1936 Aug 1 (Vol. 16, No. 1615)
.....1937 Feb 6 (Vol. 17, No. 1646)
.....1937 Mar 27-Apr 10 (Vol. 17, Nos. 1649-1651)
.....1937 Apr 24 (Vol. 18, No. 1701)
.....1937 May 8-Sep 11 (Vol. 18, Nos. 1703-1721)
.....1937 Sep 25-Dec 9 (Vol. 18, Nos. 1723-1734)
.....Continued, published in Los Angeles, California
.....1947 Jul 18
.....1947 Jul 29
.....1947 Aug
.....1947 Aug 21 (No. 2)
.....1947 Sep 4-Oct 16 (Nos. 4-10)
.....1947 Oct 30 (No. 12) The Western Comrade Llano, California
.....1915 Jun (Vol. 3, No. 2)
.....1915 Aug (Vol. 3, No. 4)
.....1915 Nov (Vol. 3, No. 7)
.....1916 Jan-Apr (Vol. 3, Nos. 9-12)
.....1916 Jun-1917 Apr (Vol. 4, Nos. 2-12)
.....1917 May-1918 Mar/Apr (Vol. 5, Nos. 1-12)
.....Continued as The Internationalist Leesville, Louisiana
.....1918 May-Jun (Vol. 6, No. 1-2) Pamphlets concerning Llano, and other printed Western ephemera Pisgah Grande Herald of Hope Los Angeles
.....Vol. 28, Nos. 1-2: 1968
.....Vol. 30, No. 5: 1970
.....Vol. 31, No. 1: 1971
.....Vol. 32, No. 1: 1972
.....Vol. 64, No. 1: 1973
.....Vol. 65, No. 4: 1974
.....Vol. 66, Nos. 1,4: 1975
.....Vol. 67, Nos. 1-3: 1976 Tassajara Zen Mountain Center, San Francisco
.....v. VI, Nos. 2-4: Fall 1967
.....v. VII, Nos. 1-4: 1968
.....v. VIII, Nos. 1-4: 1969
.....v. IX, Nos. 1-4: 1970
.....v. X, No. 1: Summer 1971
.....v. XI: 1972
.....v. XII: 1973
.....v. XIII: 1974
.....v. XIV No. 1: Summer 1975
.....v. XVI, No. 1: Winter 1978-79 Other Communities: The Beacon London
.....v. XLIV, No. 2-4 Mar-Aug 1971 Black Bart Brigade Canyon, CA
.....No.1-7: 1971-1974 The Eclectic Theosophist San Diego
.....Nos. 1-4: 1971 Mar-Aug
.....No. 12: 1972 Sep
.....Nos. 18-20: 1973 Sep-1974 Jan
.....Nos. 28-29: 1975 May-Jul Kaliflower .....Vol. 3, Nos. 19-20: 1971
.....Vol. 3, No. 23: 1971 Oct
.....Vol. 3, No. 25: 1971 Oct
.....Vol. 3, No. 29-31: 1971 Nov-Dec Newspapers discarded (holdings confirmed elsewhere): American Freeman Girard, Kansas
.....1940 May (No. 2012)
.....1940 Jul-Aug (No. 2014-2015)
.....1940 Oct-1941 Jan (No. 2017-2020) Epic News Oakland, California
.....1938 Jan 17 (page 3-4)
.....1938 Jan 24 (page 3-4)
.....1938 Jan 31 (Vol. 4, No. 36)
.....1947 Aug-Sep (Vol. 13, Nos. 10-11) Herald of Co-Operation Oakland, California
.....1933 Oct 26 (Vol. 10, No. 34) The Leesville Leader Leesville, Louisiana
.....1948 Aug 5 (Vol. 49, No. 40)
Buddhist sanghas -- California; Christian communities -- California; Collective settlements -- California; Communal living -- California; Cooperative societies -- California; Socialism -- California; Theosophy -- California; Utopias -- History -- 19th century; Fountaingrove (Calif.); Halcyon (Calif.); Holy City (Calif.); Icaria-Speranza (Collective settlement); Pisgah Grande (Calif.); Cabinet photographs; Glass negatives; Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Austin, Alice Constance, 1862-1955; Kagan, Paul, 1943-; Millsap, Walter, 1886-1971; Riker, William E.; Varian, John; Kaweah Colony; Krotona Institute of Theosophy (Ojai, Calif.); Llano Colony (Secular community); Perfect Christian Divine Way; Point Loma Theosophical Society; Tassajara Zen Mountain Center; Temple Home Association; Riker, Lucille -- Ownership; Varian, Agnes -- Ownership
- Walter Millsap Papers, 1892-1970; Series I; 4.10' (13 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Walter Millsap Papers, is organized into three subseries: Llano del Rio and Newllano, Cooperative Work after Llano, and Personal Papers.
  - LLANO DEL RIO AND NEWLLANO
    - Correspondence Between Individuals
      - Correspondence, 1916-35 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, 1936-43 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence, 1945-55 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Copy of letter from Walter Millsap to John M. Coe May 10 1955 on back of broadside entitled "Smash Graft"
        Related Archival Materials note
        See also: Oversize, box 38, folder 686
      - Correspondence, 1956-66 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        See also: Calvert, Mellie Miller. "What I Remember About Llano del Rio Colony of California," box 2, folder 50 for letter from Mellie Miller Calvert to Walter Millsap Apr 4 1958
        See also: Graves, Lee Roy, "History of Llano No. 5, Gila, New Mexico." Early draft, typescript, box 2, folder 51 for letters from Lee Roy Graves written in 1959-60
      - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence fragment (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Reports and Communiqués
      - Reports and Communiqués, 1935-71, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
        Sent to Mellie Miller Calvert Contains drafts of Llano history also found in Gateway to Freedom
        See also: Gateway to Freedom, box 1, folders 29-32
        See also: Gateway to Freedom, box 2, folders 33-37
    - Documents
      - Minutes, Board of Commissioners, 1915 Mar-Sep (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
      - Minutes, Special Assembly Meeting, 1915 Aug (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Minutes, General Assembly, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
      - Minutes, General Assembly, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Minutes, General Assembly, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Monthly Statements: W. A. Engle, 1915-18 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Mailing lists, 1920-65 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Albert Schmidt, et al vs. Llano del Rio Company of Nevada. Richard Pollard deposition, 1936 Nov 9 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Copies of various petitions, statements, and judgements, [1936], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Report on the Llano del Rio Company of Nevada by John B. Pollard, State Farm Debtor Supervisor for the State of Louisiana, 1939 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Llano History Fund. Statements and receipts, 1945, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - By-Laws of the Nevada Colony Corporation, 1965 Apr 13 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Colony News list of subscribers, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Model Articles of Incorporation for a Coop. Community, by A. H. Moore, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Miscellaneous documents, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Writings by Walter Millsap
      - "Colony News" essays, holographs, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Gateway to Freedom
        - See also: Reports and Communiqués, box 1, folders 8-10
        - Early drafts, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
          See also: Oversize, box 38, folder 687
        - Introduction: early drafts, typescript carbons, corrected, 1957 Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 30)
        - Introduction: later draft, typescript and mimeograph, corrected
          See: Oversize, box 38, folder 688
        - "Two Basic Concepts": early draft, typescript carbon, corrected, [1965] (Box 1, Folder 31)
        - "Two Basic Concepts": intermediate drafts, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
        - "The Scout for Land": typescripts, corrected (Box 2, Folder 33)
        - "Constance Austin's Housing Concept": typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34)
        - Intermediate drafts, typescripts, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 35)
        - Late draft, pages 1-12, mimeograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
        - Late draft, pages 1-40, typescript photocopy, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - "Job Harriman," typescript, corrected, 1941 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - "Memories About Llano Colony," typescript carbon, corrected, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - "The Organizational Structure of Llano"
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
        - Draft B, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
        - Draft C, mimeograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - "Reasons for Starting Llano Colony"
        - Draft A, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 43)
        - Draft B, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 44)
        - Draft C, mimeograph, corrected, 1962 Nov (Box 2, Folder 45)
          Second page of "Ucopia Newsletter" [sic] Nov. 1962
      - "Report on the Status of Llano Cooperative Colony, Newllano, Louisiana," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - "To Dixieland," typescript carbon, corrected (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Miscellaneous essays, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Writings by Others
      - Brown, Earl D. "Colony History from Earl D. Brown," holograph and typescript carbon (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Calvert, Mellie Miller. "What I Remember About Llano del Rio Colony of California", [1958 Apr 4] (Box 2, Folder 50)
        Accompanied by letter from Calvert to Millsap about the article
      - Graves, Lee Roy
        - "History of Llano No. 5, Gila, New Mexico." Early draft, typescript, [1959-60] (Box 2, Folder 51)
        - "History of Llano No. 5, Gila, New Mexico." Intermediate draft, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52)
        - "History of Llano No. 5, Gila, New Mexico." Later draft, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - Mickey, C. C. "Pleasant Memories," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - Moore, A. H.
        - "Comments on Cooperation," several drafts, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 55)
        - "Some Lessons Learned From Ten Years Residence in Llano Colony," several drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 2, Folder 56)
        - Miscellaneous writings, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 2, Folder 57)
      - Shoemaker, R. V.
        - "The Gila Episode (Gila Colony)" draft A, typescript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 58)
        - "The Gila Episode (Gila Colony)" draft B, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 59)
        - "The Gila Episode (Gila Colony)" draft C, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 60)
        - Gila Colony reminiscence, holograph, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 61)
        - "9 Years with Llano del Rio Corp. of Nevada," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 62)